Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trent History of Medicine manuscripts collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trent, Josiah.
8.5 linear feet Extent: Approximately 6000 Items
Josiah Trent (1914-1948) was a thoracic surgeon, Duke Medical Center faculty member, historian, and rare book and manuscripts collector. The Trent History of Medicine Manuscripts Collection is an artificial collection made up of 780 manuscript collections with a focus on the history of medicine or medical practice in the United States and Europe. The collections were acquired by physician and rare book and manuscripts collector Dr. Josiah Trent of Duke University. The collections range in date from a possible 1588 date to 1994, with the bulk dating from the 1750s-1980s; most consist of 1-10 items, but some are larger, up to 395 items. They are almost all correspondence collections of well-known physicians and surgeons, political figures, educators, and scientists. Some also contain reports, engravings, clippings, data, notes, invitations, and other materials. Topics range widely, and include diseases such as yellow fever and smallpox, treatments and vaccines, women's medicine, mental health and psychology, and the formation of the medical profession and its educational institutions. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
trenthommss
Language: Material in English French Italian and German
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collections with patient records containing personally-identifiable information for individuals that may still be living are closed to use until information can be redacted by staff.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Acquired by the Medical Center Library from 1936-1950 as gifts from the Josiah Trent and Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans family. Transferred to the Rubenstein Library May 2011.
Biographical Note
Josiah Trent was a thoracic surgeon, Duke Medical Center faculty member, historian, and collector of rare book and manuscripts dealing with the history of medicine and medical practice. Many of these purchases were made from Henry and Ida Schuman, rare book dealers based in Detroit, then in New York City, with whom Josiah Trent would form a long friendship. Trent was born in August 1914 in Okmulgee, Oklahoma. Trent received his Bachelor's degree from Duke University, completing his B.A. studies in three years, and entered the University of Pennsylvania Medical School medical school at age 19, graduating in 1938. He married Mary Duke Biddle in 1939. During their ten years of marriage they had four children. In those same years, besides his career as a surgeon, Trent gave lectures on the history of medicine, was chairman of the Duke Hospital Library Committee and served on the executive committee of the Friends of the Library At Duke University. He was also an Honorary Consultant of ate Army Medical Library.
Dr. Trent died at an early age from lympho-sarcoma in 1948. A few years later, his widow, Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, presented the Duke Medical Center Library with the Josiah C. Trent Collection on the History of Medicine. At the time of his death, his library contained nearly 4,000 volumes and thousands of manuscripts, including the collection of rare and unique history of medicine manuscripts described in this finding aid.
Collection Overview
The Trent History of Medicine Manuscripts Collection is an artificial collection made up of 780 manuscript collections with a focus on the history of medicine or medical practices. The collections were acquired by surgeon, historian, and rare book and manuscripts collector Dr. Josiah Trent of Duke University. The collections range in date from a possible 1588 date to 1994, with the bulk representing the 19th and 20th centuries; most consist of 1-10 items, but some are larger, up to 395 items. They were often purchased by Trent for their autograph value as well as for their historical content. They are almost all correspondence collections, but many also contain enclosed reports, clippings, data, notes, invitations, engravings, and other materials.
Correspondents include many well-known physicians and surgeons, political figures, educators, and scientists, with an emphasis on physicians and scientists from the United States, France, England, Italy, and Germany. Among the most notable individuals are: Abigail and John Adams; Elizabeth Blackwell; Daniel Drake; Benjamin Franklin; Oliver Wendell Holmes; Alexander von Humboldt; Thomas Jefferson; Howard Atwood Kelly; Alexander Marcet; Silas Weir Mitchell; Florence Nightingale; Sir William Osler; Louis Pasteur; Frank Lester Pleadwell; Earle Pliny; John Ridlon; Benjamin Rush; Viscount John Jervis St. Vincent; Sir James Young Simpson; Lyman Spalding; Mary Edwards Walker; and Benjamin Waterhouse.
Topics range widely, and include epidiemology, with a focus on yellow fever, cholera, cancer, and smallpox; treatments and vaccines; history of surgery and anesthesia; the new fields of neurology, pulmonology, and cardiology; gynecology and women's health topics; mental health and psychology; pharmacology; medical publishing and research; military medicine during the Revolutionary War, the Civil War, World War I, and other conflicts; the formation of the medical profession and its educational institutions; and the personal affairs of the individuals represented in the papers. Childhood diseases and pediatrics are not common themes but there are a few references to them, notably Abigail Adams discussion of vaccinating children against smallpox.
The 781 small collections individually listed in this finding aid are also cataloged individually as separate collections in the Duke Libraries online catalog, but are physically housed together as the Trent History of Medicine Manuscripts Collection. Entries are arranged alphabetically by author/creator and include the chief author of the material, date range, number of items, and a brief summary of the content. Abbreviations used include ALS: Autograph Letter Signed (hand-written and signed by same individual); ANS: Autograph Note, Signed; and TLS: Typed Letter Signed.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
The John Ridlon Papers within the Trent Manuscripts Collection contain case summaries with personally-identifiable information such as full names, dating from the early 20th century. Although the individuals represented are probably deceased, these records and any other similar records are not publicly accessible until the information has been redacted. Please contact the Research Services staff before coming to use this collection.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Trent, Josiah C. (Josiah Charles), 1914-1948.; Autographs -- Collections; Disease; Medical education -- History; Medicine -- History; Medicine -- Europe -- History; Medicine -- United States -- History; Mental illness; Physicians; Physicians -- England -- Correspondence; Physicians -- France -- Correspondence; Physicians -- Germany -- Correspondence; Physicians -- Italy -- Correspondence; Physicians -- United States -- Correspondence; Psychology -- History; Smallpox; Surgery -- History; Vaccines -- History; Women -- Health and hygiene -- History; Yellow fever; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Related Material
The History of Medicine Collections at Duke University also house many other manuscript collections and books directly related to the authors or content of the Trent Manuscripts Collection. For assistance, please consult with the Curator of the History of Medicine Collections.
Contents of Collection
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Abderhalden, Emil, 1877-1950. Letter, 1919, May 26, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Professor of physiology at Berne and Halle. In this letter (TLS), Abderhalden acknowledges the receipt of a letter, speaks of the general conditions in Germany, and solicits Dr. Strauss' contribution to the Handbook of methods in biological investigations.
  - Abercrombie, John, 1780-1844. Letter, 1839 and undated, (3 items) (Box 1)
    Scottish physician and pathologist. Three letters (ALS), including a letter of reference, dated May 27, 1839, Edinburgh, for Dr. William Pirrie.
  - Acland, Henry Wentworth, 1815-1900. Letters, 1868-1877 and undated, (3 items) (Box 1)
    Professor of Physic at the University of Oxford. Three letters (ALS), two to his father, and one confidential letter regarding concerns about a hospital.
  - Adamos. Manuscript, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Manuscript in an anonymous hand. Four pages of a materia medica, of which one section bears the title "The Efforts and Vertuos: with the severall use of Venice Triache".
  - Adams, Abigail, 1744-1818. Letters, 1797-1798, (6 items) (Box 1)
    Wife of John Adams, second President of the United States. Six letters (ALS) to Mrs. Black concerning Mr. and Mrs. Hall, who died in the yellow fever epidemic of 1797, and their orphaned infant daughter. Mr. Hall was treated by Dr. Benjamin Rush and Dr. John Redman Coxe. The infant was later inoculated for smallpox by Dr. Rush. Includes transcriptions.
  - Adams, Charles Baker, 1814-1853, Letter, 1851, Nov. 17, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. naturalist and zoologist. Letter (ALS) acknowledges receipt of parcel of South African and other shells. Refers to Adams' work on Panamanian shells.
  - Adams, John, 1735-1826. Letter, 1821, June 6, (1 item) (Box 14 (oversize))
    Second president of the United States (1797-1801). In this letter (ALS) written towards the end of his life to President James Monroe, Adams petitions for the financial support of physician and Harvard Medical School professor Benjamin Waterhouse, suggesting that Waterhouse's present difficulties are a result of his outspoken support of "the Union." Includes an engraving of John Adams. Both mounted on board.
  - Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873. Letters, 1836-1861, (2 items) (Box 1)
    Swiss-born U.S. naturalist, geologist and teacher. Two letters (ALS). The first, in German, to fellow zoologist Dr. Kaup of Darmstadt. The second, in French, to W. G. Abel, a musician who applied for a position at Agassiz's school for girls.
  - Agnew, David Hayes, 1818-1892. Letters, 1857-1880, (3 items) (Box 1)
    Surgeon and teacher of anatomy and surgery in Philadelphia. Three letters (ALS), including a letter of recommendation for R. G. Barclay to the Physicians and Surgeons of St. Joseph's Hospital.
  - Aikin, John, 1747-1822. Letter, 1807, May 30, (1 item) (Box 1)
    English physician and author. Letter (ALS) regarding an article submitted by Taylor to the Athenaeum, a journal edited by Aikin.
  - Alard Prosper. Diploma, 1808, June 30, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Diploma of membership in the society, "Regia matritensis Academia". Bears seal of society and signatures of Ignatius Maria Ruiz, Joseph Mozinnus, Joseph Anthony à Capdeosta, Bañarès, and Salvadore X. Coronado.
  - Albin, Maurice S. Calling card, 1976, Oct. 31, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Calling card with a signed note to Dr. Robert H. Wilkins.
  - Alexander, Stephen, 1806-1883. Letter, 1837, June 9, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. astronomer and professor of astronomy at Princeton University. Letter (ALS) reports the whereabouts and activities of Joseph Henry, his brother-in-law, and A.D. Bache and lists the "scientific men of London" with whom they were in contact, including Faraday, Wheatstone, Babbage, Barlow, Dr. Gregory and a Professor Powell of Oxford.
  - Alibert, Jean-Louis-Marie, 1768-1837. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    French physician and dermatologist. Letter (ALS) describes a treatment for a skin condition. Includes translation.
  - Andral, Gabriel, 1797-1876. Letter, 1827, July 10, (1 item) (Box 1)
    French physician. Letter (ALS) reports that upon examination a patient was diagnosed with dyspepsia. Describes an appropriate course of treatment. Includes translation.
  - Anfinsen, Christian Boehmer, 1916-1995. Letter, 1827, July 10, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. biochemist; received 1972 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. A note (ANS) written on the letterhead of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.
  - Anonymous. Letter, 1871, Oct. 22, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Letter concerning disagreement among hospital staff.
  - Antisell, Thomas, 1817-1893. 1849, Jan. 26, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. physician, geologist and chemist. Letter (ALS) acknowledges the receipt of $4.12 as balance of the proceeds arising from the delivery of lectures. Expresses gratitude for the opportunity to speak before a New York audience.
  - Apostoli, Georges, 1847-1900. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Letter (ALS) informs recipient that Apostoli will send a recent published thesis on his electrical treatment of fibromata.
  - Armour, Donald John, 1864-1933. Letter, 1904, June 10, (1 item) (Box 1)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS) acknowledges the receipt of a letter and check. Expresses gratification that he has been able to provide not only professional services, but also those of a friend.
  - Armstrong, John, 1709-1779. Letters, 1775, [1779], and undated, (4 items) (Box 1)
    English physician and essayist. Three letters (ALS) and an engraved portrait of Armstrong. One letter details dinner at the Shakespeare Inn.
  - Arnal, Jean Louis, 1806-1871. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Physician of Paris. Note (ANS).
  - Arsonval, Jacques Arsène d', 1851-1940. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    French physician and physicist. Letter (ALS) to "Cher Confrère et Ami"
  - Askew, Anthony, 1722-1774. Letter, 1745-1749, (5 items) (Box 1)
    English physician, classical scholar, and collector. Five letters (ALS). Askew writes to Richard Mead and to his father, Dr. Adam Askew, about his travels, including visits to the library at Wolfenbüttel, and the Herculaneum. He discusses his classical studies, commenting on the work of various classicists including Richard Dawes, Richard Bentley, John Mill, and Johann Jacob Reiske.
  - Atkins, Arthur F. Letter, 1866, Jan. 17, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Application for a license as a physician of cancers by Arthur F. Atkins. Registered by John A. Boyden. Atkins is assessed a $10.00 tax.
  - Austin, Benjamin W. Papers, 1866-1902 and undated, (11 items) (Box 1)
    Secretary of the Northwestern Literary and Historical Society of Sioux City, Iowa, and later of the Trinity Historical Society of Oak Cliff and Dallas, Texas. Letters (ALS), clippings, prints and a photo. These items form part of the autograph and signed letter collection of Benjamin W. Austin. Items include letters from Thomas Dunn English, Sir Edward Frankland, Sarah Hackett Stevenson and Joseph Leidy. There are other papers of Austin held in the Rubenstein Library.
  - Babington, Benjamin Guy, 1794-1866. note, undated, (1 item) (Box 1)
    English physician and linguist. Note (ANS). Accepts an invitation to dinner.
  - Baccelli, Guido, 1832-1916. Letter, 1872, Apr. 6, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Italian physician and professor of anatomy. Note (ANS). Prescribes medication.
  - Bache, Franklin, 1792-1864. Letter, 1823, Nov. 29, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. physician and chemist. Letter (ALS). Reports results of the analysis of a mineral water sample left by Dr. La Roche.
  - Backus, Nathaniel, 1669-1728. Deed, 1708, Jan. 28, (1 item) (Opaperfolder 1)
    Resident of Norwich, Mass., perhaps a physician. Deed of land purchase, Norwich, Conn. Signed by Backus, witnessed by Solomon Tracy and Benajah Bushnell. Acknowledged by Richard Bushnell, Justice of the Peace.
  - Baginsky, Adolf, 1843-1918. Enrollment book, 1865-1866, (1 item) (Box 1)
    This signed document is a record of lectures attended at the Königliche Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität, Berlin.
  - Bailey, Jacob Whitman, 1811-1857. Letter, 1834, Sept. 23, (1 item) (Box 1)
    U.S. botanist, chemist and geologist. Letter (ALS). Writes about botanical specimens and his activities at West Point Military Academy.
  - Baillarger, Jules Gabriel François, 1809-1890. Letters, 1840 and undated, (2 items) (Box 1)
    French psychiatrist. Two letters (ALS). One is a certificate to commit a female patient.
  - Baillie, Matthew, 1761-1823. Letters, 1819-1820 and undated, (5 items) (Box 1)
    Scottish physician and pathologist. Two letters (ALS), one holograph note, and two clippings. Includes a prescription "for Dewar Esqr." and a note to "Richard Reeves Esq."
  - Baldwin, Thomas. Deed, 1708, Jan. 28, (1 item) (Opaperfolder 2)
    Deed of land purchase, written in Norwich, Conn., addressed to Israel Lothrup. Witnessed by Solomon Tracy and Benajah Bushnell. Acknowledged by Richard Bushnell, Justice of the Peace.
  - Barbancey, Jacqueline (Simon de Villevieille, Jacqueline Nicole). Letter, 1946, Mar. 1, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Letter (ALS). Tipped in Duke Medical Center Library Historical Collection copy of her work, Un cas célèbre de mélancolie, Lord Byron. Letter accompanied book, which was given to an unknown recipient. The letter excuses the "poor quality" of the work, explaining the various circumstances under which the work was written.
  - Barclay, Robert G. (Gutzlaff), 1832-1876. Papers, 1855-1867 and undated, (34 items) (Box 1)
    Virginia-born physician who graduated from Jefferson Medical College in 1857 and went to Syria to practice medicine there from 1859-1866; also studied and taught at the University of Pennsylvania. Then resided in Hillsboro Ala., where he was a cotton planter and physician; died Nov. 19, 1876. Papers consist of several letters to Barclay, printed matriculation cards from Jefferson Medical College (in one Barclay is referred to as being from the state of Jerusalem, Palestine), a phrenological chart, a printed speech by a James Barclay to Congress (a relative?), and various notices. One letter, written in 1857 by prominent physician Robley Dunglison, is in support of his appointment as physician at Philadelphia Hospital. Also includes a letter to "Dr. Blackler" at the American Mission at the City of Jerusalem, undated, apparently accompanying two sample bottles of "Ayer's Cherry Pectoral." A letter from 1941 gives biographical details about Dr. Barclay. A portrait of Dr. Barclay is also held in the History of Medicine Collections Picture File at Duke, and his diplomas are housed separately.
  - Bard, Samuel, 1742-1821. Papers, 1789-1811, (4 items) (Box 1, Opaperfolder 3)
    New York physician and obstetrician. Four documents. Receipt of payment by the estate of Robert C. Livingston to Samuel Bard; license to practice medicine, issued by the Medical Society of Dutchess County, New York, to Dr. Larry G. Hall; two blank certificates (in Latin) of membership in the New York Medical Society, signed by John Bard (1716-1799), Samuel Bard's father.
  - Bardeleben, Adolf, 1819-1895. Letter, 1853, June 11, (1 item) (Box 1)
    German surgeon. Letter (ALS) concerning a post-mortem examination in a case of cancer of the brain.
  - Barker, Fordyce, 1819-1891. Papers, 1856-1891, (4 items) (Box 1)
    U.S. obstetrician and gynecologist. Four notes (ANS). One note thanks Mr. R. H. Simpson for the invitation to hear Edward Everett. Another note informs Mr. Lipton that Barker will be unable to attend a meeting of the Bowdoin Alumni Association.
  - Barney, John P. Letter, 1795, Sept. 19, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Holograph letter, unsigned. Relates how the yellow fever epidemic has affected neighbors and acquaintances. Reports that many conceal their illness for fear of being carried to and dying in Bellevue Hospital.
  - Bartels, Paul, 1874-1914. Letters, 1905 June-Oct., (3 items) (Box 1)
    German anatomist and anthropologist. Two letters (ALS) and one postcard signed. Discusses the journal, Die Nekrologe. Makes arrangements for editing and publishing his late father's unfinished work.
  - Bartlett, Elisha, 1804-1855. Letters, 1839-1841, (2 items) (Box 1)
    New England physician. Two letters (ALS), including a letter to his father-in-law, John Slater, a New England textile manufacturer, regarding general financial and family matters.
  - Bartlett, Josiah, 1759-1820. Letters, 1817, Oct. 2, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Physician of Massachusetts. Certificate of the Massachusetts Medical Society, that Josiah Lamson is qualified to practice medicine. Signed by, among others, Josiah Bartlett and Aaron Dexter.
  - Bartlett, Levi, 1763-1828. Letters, 1789-1802, (7 items) (Box 1)
    Physician of Kingston, New Hampshire. Seven letters (ALS). Letter from Bartlett to the engraver Joseph Callender. Letters to Bartlett from his brother, Dr. Josiah Bartlett, and from Drs. Thomas Kittridge and Amos Gale. Letters from J. Bartlett and Gale relate to the cowpox virus and Benjamin Waterhouse's efforts to regulate its use.
  - Barton, John Rhea, 1794-1871. Letter, 1826, Dec. 22, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Surgeon, Philadelphia Almshouse. Letter (ALS) of reference for Mr. Andrew Ellicot Kennedy.
  - Bassi, Agostino, 1773-1856. Letters, 1851, Sept. 29, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Italian bacteriologist and micro-pathologist. Letter (LS) presenting his most recent work.
  - Bassini, Edoardo, 1844-1924. Letter, 1890, Dec. 11, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Italian surgeon and professor of surgery. Thank you note (ANS) for courtesies shown him in Vienna.
  - Baumes, Jean Baptiste Timothée, 1756-1828. Letter, 1803, Feb. 20, (1 item) (Box 1)
    French physician and professor of medicine. Letter (ALS) relates the activities of the Société de Médecine-pratique de Montpellier and solicits Julia's help in the commission of various errands. M. Bouillon-Lagrange is mentioned.
  - Beattie, William, 1793-1875. Letters, 1854-1875, (3 items) (Box 1)
    English physician and writer. Two letters (ALS) and a clipping, including a letter to John Britton regarding Britton's autobiography.
  - Beaumont William, 1785-1853. Letters, 1816-1944, (5 items) (Box 1)
    U.S. Army surgeon. Material includes a letter (ALS), reprints, holograph notes. All material relates to the letter, from Commodore Thomas Macdonough to B. W. Crowninshield, Secretary of the Navy, recommending William Beaumont for service in the Navy.
  - Beck, Charles Frederick, b. 1806. Papers, 1819-1845, (6 items) (Box 1)
    A collection of diplomas and certificates from the University of Pennsylvania, the Medical Society of Philadelphia, the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, and the American Philosophical Society of Philadelphia, bearing various signatures, including those of A. D. Bache, Franklin Bache, John K. Kane, Robley Dunglison, Philip Syng Physick, Joseph Parrish, Samuel Jackson, John Redman Coxe, Thomas C. James, Robert Hare, William Gibson, William E. Horner, and William Dewees.
  - Beck, Lewis Caleb, 1798-1853. Letter, [Between 1824 and 1826], June 20, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Physician, botanist and chemist, of New York state. Letter (ALS) explaining that he is unable to remain in Troy until July 2nd due to other engagements.
  - Beck, Theodric Romeyn, 1791-1855. Letter, [Between 1815 and 1840], (1 item) (Box 1)